CURRICULUM VITAE DR. SAMSON M. KAMAU

BIO DATA:

Date of birth 14th August 1971

Marital status Married with three children.

Nationality Kenyan

Telephone no. Mobile: 0719189797, Office: 0719018860,

Email address Spouse: 0722774305 skamau1998@gmail.com

CARRER OBJECTIVE

A change oriented executive keen on improving organization systems, structures and processes.

PROFESSIONAL PROFILE

A change-oriented leader with over twenty years of experience of work gained from diverse industry experience including Fast-Moving Consumer Goods (FMCG), telecommunication, / energy, management consultancy & building industry.

I uphold high level of integrity, honesty, and passion in what I do. I believe in teamwork and team results.

EDUCATION

2013 – 2017: Doctor of Philosophy in Organization Development & Transformation (PhOD), Cebu Doctor's University, Cebu City, Philippines

1996 – 1997: Master of Business Administration (Marketing Management) Kenyatta University, Kenya

1990 - 1995: Bachelor of Commerce (BCom), Kenyatta University, Kenya

2006 - Postgraduate diploma in Marketing (Marketing Society of Kenya)

WORKING EXPERIENCE

June 2021 - to date

Manager, Risk and Compliance, KENYA ELECTRICITY TRANSMISSION COMPANY LTD, Nairobi, Kenya (KETRACO)

Objective: To provide advisory services to management on risk, quality assurance and compliance to ensure efficiency of the company operations.

Reporting: General Manager, Strategy, Research & Compliance

Key Tasks:

- Coordinate development, review, implementation, and monitoring of quality management procedures.
- Coordinate management of identified risks and implement mitigating strategies
- Coordinate compliance of the company policies and those of statutory in nature.

December 2013 - June 2021

Manager, Business Development, KENYA ELECTRICITY TRANSMISSION COMPANY LTD, Nairobi, Kenya (KETRACO)

Objective - To offer strategic leadership in the identification and development of commercial income streams for financial sustainability.

Reporting: General Manager, Strategy, Research & Compliance

Key Tasks:

- Build and maintain commercial income streams for KETRACO
- Identify business opportunities for KETRACO
- Develop and implement business proposals
- Secure relevant business licenses
- Negotiate contracts with clients.
- Produce accurate management reports

Achievements

- Developed fiber business model from zero revenue to Ksh130M per year in fy 2020/21.
- Fiber revenue contributing immensely to internally generated income
- Implementing a tier 4 data centre as a new business strategy
- Created local and regional business network

November 2012 - October 2013

Regional Sales & Marketing Manager, KALUWORKS LTD Mombasa, Kenya

Objective: - To initiate business development strategies to improve Nairobi

Regional sales

Reporting: Managing Director

Key Tasks:

Develop a distribution strategy to:

- Penetrate Nairobi region to improve revenue / market share
- Build brand equity
- Improve the sales operations in Nairobi including managing staff
- Prepare monthly reports on sales and competition for management

Achievement

- Developed a distribution strategy
- Built a very strong industry expert network to support the business
- Improved Nairobi Region revenue contribution by 30% through market penetration.

Dec 2011 - July 2012

Head of Strategy & Business Development, MELLECH GROUP, Nairobi, Kenya

Objective: - To develop Corporate and Business Development strategies to expand the market in Kenya, South Sudan and Rwanda for the Construction & Telecom business.

Reporting: Chief Executive Officer

Key Tasks

- Identify and develop new business opportunities
- Lead in the development of operational and strategic plan
- Develop and monitor business development strategies
- Lead and manage business development team
- Develop monthly reports for management

Achievement

Involved in formulation and implementation of corporate strategy

February 2010 - Nov 2011

Director, Business Development, CORAT Africa, Nairobi, Kenya

Objective: - To establish business development department, formulate business development strategies and deepen the market

Reporting: The Managing Director

Key Tasks

- Establish the department / function
- Develop marketing strategies for the three commercial streams of the organization
- Develop annual budgets for the department
- Develop new business streams by identifying new markets

Achievement

- Established the business development department
- Penetrated product in the targeted market resulting in improved revenue/profit
- Developed a new business stream in West Africa

April 2005 - Jan 2010

Business Development Manager, MANSON HART KENYA LTD Nairobi, Kenya

Objective: - To reverse falling sales revenue and profitability in a competitive environment by developing & implementing new strategies

Reporting: The General Manager

Key Tasks

- Develop marketing strategies
- Manage sales/ marketing staff
- Preparing and monitoring operational budgets
- Brand building
- Briefing the Board on performance

Achievements

- Introduced new products eg paving blocks
- Team leader in development of the first strategic plan (2006 2010)
- Streamlined the sales operations efficiency especially on sales agents
- Developed a distribution strategy and recruited distributors in major towns.

June 2000-April 2005

Customer Service Representative, UNILEVER KENYA

Nairobi, Kenya

Objective: To manage assigned territory Key Distributors

Reporting: Area Sales Manager

Key Tasks

- Manage key distributors to maximize coverage / sales / revenue
- Manage all territory promotional activities
- Improve sales by identifying new markets

Achievements

- Introduced new products
- Increased market coverage by 30% in assigned territory
- Recruited new distributors

SHORT COURSES ATTENDED

- Several ISO courses undertaken
- Servant Leadership training, Nairobi
- Teaching Negotiation in Organizations, Harvard University
- Strategic Negotiation Skills, South Africa
- Policy Formulation, Analysis and Advocacy, Nairobi
- Knowledge Management, Nairobi
- Supervisory Skills, Nairobi
- Strategy Review & Leadership, Nairobi
- Policy Formulation, Analysis and Advocacy
- Knowledge Management, Nairobi
- Supervisory Skills, Nairobi
- Project Management, Nairobi
- Strategic approaches, Denmark
- Corporate Governance, Nairobi
- Governance and Conflict Management, Naivasha
- Certified Fiber Optic Technician, Nairobi
- Power Purchase Agreements, London
- Equipping Fund Raising Professionals, Nairobi
- Balanced Scorecard, Nairobi
- Total Performance Management, Nairobi
- Statistical Package for Social Sciences (SPSS), Nairobi
- Effective Customer care, Nairobi

- Problem solving and conflict management, Nairobi
- Time Management, Nairobi
- Computer packages, Nairobi
- Telecom, datacom and networking for non-engineers professionals, Canada
- Voice over IP, security, 5G and IoT, Canada

BOARD MEMBERSHIP

- Local Church Council Deliverance Church, Kasarani
- Ex-Board Chairman- Feed The Children Kenya, 2011 2018
- Ex Board member, Build Africa, 2011-2016
- Member- Marketing Society of Kenya

COMMITTEE APPOINTMENT AT KETRACO

- Member of the strategic plan working group
- Member of the research and development coordinating team
- Team leader ISO management systems
- Chairman –Fundraising committee (EAPP)
- Chairman Benevolent Fund
- Chairman of the Alcohol and drugs prevention committee
- Member of the monitoring and evaluation steering committee
- Member of the safety and health committee
- Member of the culture change team
- Member of the Covid -19 Crisis management team
- Company signatory of all payments

INTERPERSONAL SKILLS/

STRENGTHS

- Good people management skills
- Change oriented mindset
- Good negotiator

INTERESTS

- Travelling
- Supporting and sharing gospel with prisoners
- Watching documentaries
- Listening to gospel music

REFEREES

Mr Samuel Sangura	Dr. Joshua Amwayi	Mr. Peter Murage
Director	KETRACO	Head of Hospitality
Taxpert Consultants	P.O Box 34942 – 00100,	Rusinga School
Ltd,P.O Box 21624 -	Nairobi.	P.O Box 25088 -
00100, Nairobi.	Tel: +254 722321001	00603,Lavington,
Tel: 0722863284	Email:	Nairobi. Tel: +254
Email:	jamwayi@ketraco.co.ke	722306848
sssimiyu@taxpert.co.k		Email:
e		pmurage@rusinga.ac.
		<u>ke</u>